Hello everyone, welcome to this training on HTTP and HTTPS fundamentals, let's start from
the very beginning HTTP stands for hypertext transfer protocol. Think of it as the language
that your web browser speaks to communicate with websites. HTTP is the set of rules for
this conversion and basically it's unsecured. Let's discuss about what is HTTPS, HTTP basically
HTTP plus S stands for secure. So the full form will be hypertext transfer protocol
secure and it is an encrypted layer, it is an encrypted, encrypted form. With regular HTTP anyone
can listen in on the conversation between your browser and the website, okay. So basically
it's a part. So it will be you and me, okay. So we are doing a communication, we are
doing a communication by using HTTP, okay. It's HTTP, okay. And what will be happen in HTTP?
Like anyone would like to, would like to hear our conversation or anyone would like to see
our conversation. So a guy who comes up with the name with let's say attacker, okay.
So this guy is a third party, okay. So this guy is the third party, okay. So he wanted
to listen our conversation between of this service, between of this communication, right.
So this is the basic thing, this is the HTTP main like loophole, okay. So where like
anyone can listen in on the conversation between your browser and the website. So it's
like talking loudly in a public place, okay. But what will happen in HTTPS? What will happen
in HTTPS? The conversation is encrypted. So this will be encrypted, totally encrypted, okay.
No one can, this will be totally encrypted. It's like a whispering in a secret code, okay. That
only you and the website understand. So like you just, when you just connect this call
to me, okay. You created a code which is a very encrypted code, ex, y, z. Let's say this
code, okay. And this code will be at this will be the encrypted code. And on the other hand,
I will, I will get the decrypted code, okay. So let's say, yeah, let's say ex, ex, y, z,
one. So this is a decrypted code, okay. So when I will, I will like, I got a connection
from you, like I got a call from you, okay. So I need to just decode that code first, okay.
Then automatically it will decode the code and we will just communicate from this, this
HTTPS connection. So that is the main difference between HTTP and HTTPS. So when do we
use HTTPS? Basically, when we are using banking apps, okay, when we using banking apps,
banking apps or website, shopping, shopping site, okay, like like Amazon, okay, flip card,
this kinds of shopping sites, eBay, right. So email services, when we are email services
like Google, Google Mills service or Yahoo, okay. And when we are doing social media, okay,
when we are doing social media, then we need basically secured connection. So basically any
site handling sensitive information, like for that time, we need to use HTTPS. So how to
spot HTTPS? How to spot HTTPS? Basically, you need to look for a paddle lock, a paddle
lock icon, okay, like like, okay, like this. When you, a paddle lock icon in your browser
address bar, here you can see, okay, let's see, Google.com, let's see, Google.com.
Basically, they are using HTTPS connection, right. So when you are seeing the paddle lock
or HTTPS, okay, so the URL start with HTTPS, not HTTP, okay. So that is the part of HTTPS,
okay. Now let's talk about how HTTPS works. So request response cycle, there will be a method
which will be request response cycle. So let me explain the basic flow, you type a URL,
like, like, let's say a test, test.com, let's say test.com in your browser, okay. You type
test.com in your browser, okay, and browser sends the request to the server, okay. And it
will, this test.com, there, there will be a server, okay. Now let's say this is the just
commit, let's create this first. Now let's say, this is the ear browser, okay. This is your browser.
And in your browser address bar, you just type, takes.com or sorry, test.com, okay.
You just type, test.com. Now what will happen? Now a browser will send a request to the, to
the, this server, test.com server, okay. Okay. So like, like this, it will, it will communicate
here, can I have your homepage? So it's sending the request and it will, it will ask
that he, can I have your homepage and server will process the request and prepare the response,
okay. So if, okay, and then it will, it will give you a response with sends us, server
sends our response back, show here's the homepage of HTML, homepage HTML in images, etc.
Okay. And browser displays the page for you to see, okay. So this happens within a
millisecond every time you visit a website. Thank you.